<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>By the Queene. A proclamation to forbid all maner of persons to resort to any townes held by the French Kings rebels, or to traffique with any of them, vpon paine to be punished as traitors with a declaration of the iust causes of the said prohibition. Giuen vnder her Maiesties signet at Greenwich the xiiij. day of Aprill 1591, and of her Maiesties reigne the xxxiij. yere.</title>
            <title>Proclamations. 1591-04-14</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21872</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 8202</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115443</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850662</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850662</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15883</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21872)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15883)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 565:66)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>By the Queene. A proclamation to forbid all maner of persons to resort to any townes held by the French Kings rebels, or to traffique with any of them, vpon paine to be punished as traitors with a declaration of the iust causes of the said prohibition. Giuen vnder her Maiesties signet at Greenwich the xiiij. day of Aprill 1591, and of her Maiesties reigne the xxxiij. yere.</title>
                  <title>Proclamations. 1591-04-14</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1558-1603 : Elizabeth I)</author>
                  <author>Elizabeth I, Queen of England, 1533-1603.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>2 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By the deputies of Christopher Barker, printer to the Queenes most excellent Maiestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1591]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  HenryIV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  HenryIV, 1589-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England --  Proclamations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="proclamation">
            <pb facs="tcp:15883:1"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>By the Queene.</hi> A Proclamation to forbid all maner of perſons to reſort to any Townes held by the French Kings rebels, or to traffique with any of them, vpon paine to be puniſhed as Traitors: with a declaration of the iust cauſes of the ſaid prohibition. Giuen vnder her Maiesties ſignet at <hi>Greenwich</hi> the xiiij. day of Aprill <hi>1591,</hi> and of her Maiesties reigne the xxxiij. yere.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Queenes Maieſtie conſidering the continuance of the vnnatural rebellion of a multitude of the French kings Subiectes in Fraunce, againſt their moſt lawfull king, heretofore king of Nauarre, and now iuſtly entituled Henry the fourth king of Fraunce and Nauarre, being recommended to the realme by the laſt king before his death, in preſence of all the Princes of the bloud, and of the reſt of the Nobilitie of the Realme, to be his moſt lawfull ſucceſſor of the Crowne, and ſo immediatly vpon the death of the ſaide late French king, accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and acknowledged by all the ſaide Princes of the Bloud, inheritable to the crowne, without exception of any one of the ſame princes Eccleſiaſtical or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall: And in like maner from the death of the laſt king, ſerued and obeyed by all the auncient officers of the Crowne, and namely by all the Marſhals of Fraunce, the principall officers of that Realme, and by the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of all the Noble men, gouernors of the Prouinces. And that it now manifeſtly appeareth, that this vnnaturall rebellion is fauoured by none of the auncient byrth of Fraunce, but by a very fewe of a ſtrange bloud, lately brought in, and planted by marriages in Fraunce, being onely branches depending of the houſe of Lorraine, which is no naturall member of the Crowne of Fraunce to poſſeſſe the ſame: Therefore her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie hath for theſe and many other cauſes in the ſight of Almightie God very iuſt, and to the world moſt hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, bene moued to yeelde to the ſaid king her good brother and confederate, her fauour, both in approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his right, and wiſhing to him proſperitie againſt his rebels, as ſhe thinketh there is no Monarch, nor any Soueraigne Potentate in all Chriſtendome but doth the like, ſauing onely one: who not contented with all the kingdomes and dominions which his moſt noble father left him, by reaſon of his aboundant riches brought to him out of his Indies, attempteth to augment his eſtate by encroching to himſelfe the dominions of his neighbors. And for that purpoſe, her Maieſtie hath alſo according to ſuch power as God hath giuen to her, and as ſhe may conueniently yeelde with regarde to her owne eſtate, giuen to the ſaid moſt Chriſtian king ſome ſuccours, and ſo mindeth to continue her fauours, as manifeſtly hath, and dayly is ſeene, both to all ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and to her owne people, and by none miſliked but by the rebels and the king aboue deſcribed, who at this day is manifeſtly ſeene, that if he were diſpoſed to liue in peace, and be contented with his owne dominions, and not ſeeke the dominions of any others, Chriſtendome were to enioy an vniuerſall peace, without any noyſe of warre in any countrie or corner of Chriſtendome. And now her Maieſtie finding that this populer rebellion againſt the ſaid king, is fedde and maintained in ſundry Port Townes of Fraunce, and ſpecially in Norman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and Britaine, where the people liue by bringing to them forreine marchandize, and by vent of their owne, and by receiuing of ſuccours of victuals &amp; munitions of warre from forraine countries, without which the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels in their Ports could neither continue their rebellion, nor yet relieue their fellowe rebels within the land: Hath thought it meete, that although her ſubiects ought in reaſon of themſelues to haue conſidered as much, to will and charge, and ſo ſhe doth expreſſely will, charge, and commaunde, all maner her owne naturall Subiects, and all other perſons reſorting to her realme, to forbeare from repayring to any Porte or Creeke of Picardie, Normandie, or Britaine, where the Rulers of the ſame Portes or Creekes doe not manifeſtly obey the French king, and that in no manner, directly or indirectly, they doe cary or ſend any Marchandize, victual, or munition to any Port or Towne, that doeth diſobey the French king, or doe vſe any trade of buying or ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by bartering or by exchange with any of the kings rebels, or with their adherents either in Fraunce, or fraudulently here in England or elſewhere: vpon paine that whoſoeuer ſhall attempt the contrarie, the ſame ſhall be puniſhed as Traitors, and relieuers and ſuccourers of her Maieſties enemies. For ſuch her Maieſtie doth iudge the ſaid kings rebels to be, in that they haue and doe to their power, declare themſelues to be ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb facs="tcp:15883:2"/> to her Maieſtie and her Subiectes, as by their hoſtile actions againſt her Maieſties ſubiectes, hath in many partes manifeſtly appeared. As in like ſorte alſo the king of Scottes her good brother, and a friend and auncient Allie to the Crowne of France, hath publiquely declared himſelfe an enemie to the ſaid rebels, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> prohibited his Subiects from trading in any ſorte with the rebels of Fraunce: notwithſtanding ſome of the heads of the rebellion, to his great miſliking, are by the houſe of Lorraine of kinred to him.</p>
            <p>And becauſe her Maieſtie is informed, that though many of her ſecretly euill diſpoſed ſubiects do outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſhew themſelues not to haue a minde to repaire to the ports poſſeſſed by the foreſaid Rebels, but colourably doe in her Maieſties ports lade their wares, and make their entries with the officers of the Cuſtomehouſes, and take their cockets, as thereby to carrie the ſame to the ports of France which are knowen to obey the French king: Or ſometimes lading of vitailes, make their entries to repaire only to other ports of the realme, and ſometimes to the iſles of Iernſey or Garnſey, and yet moſt corruptly, and againſt their loyaltie, for gaine or other corruption, they doe craftily repaire with the ſaid merchandiſe and vitailes, yea and by ſtealth with munition, as pouder, ſhot, copper, and other habiſlements of warre, to the ports manifeſtly held by the Rebels: For repreſſing of which abuſe, her Maieſtie chargeth and commandeth all her officers of her Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomehouſes, to haue good regard to the conditions of all that ſhall lade any wares to be tranſported out of the realme by ſea, or of vitaile from port to port. And if they ſhall haue any ſuſpition that the ſaid wares or vitailes ſo to be laden, might be carried to the Rebels townes in France, they ſhall not ſuffer any ſuch to depart with their lading, except the owners and laders ſhall both by their corporall othe, and by bond with ſureties to the double value of the things laden, giue aſſurance, and cleere themſelues of all ſuſpition, that no part of their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhall by them, or by any for them, be carried to any towne of the Rebels in France. And if any offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of the ports ſhall hereafter know, or be informed of any being either the merchant, the owner, or the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the ſhippe, or ſailer, that ſhall offend to the contrary of this her Maieſties proclamation, and ſhall not ſpeedily giue notice thereof to the Lord Treaſurer of England, or to the Lords of the Priuie councell, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent the perſons offending, and the ſhips alſo may be apprehended: ſuch officer for concealing thereof, ſhall loſe all offices in the port for euer, and ſhall ſuffer cloſe impriſonment one whole yeere without baile, and yeeld ſuch fine to her Maieſtie, as his condition may endure. And if any Viceadmirall or his deputie, ſhall know, or be informed of any perſon that ſhall offend to the contrary of this proclamation, and ſhall not ſpeedily giue notice thereof to the Lord Admirall, or in the Fiue ports to the Lord Warden, or to the Priuie councell: the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo concealing the ſame, ſhall looſe his office for euer, and ſuffer cloſe impriſonment the ſpace of one whole yere, and likewiſe yeeld ſuch fine, as his condition ſhall endure.</p>
            <closer>God ſaue the Queene.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at London by the Deputies of Chriſtopher Barker, Printer to the Queenes moſt excellent Maieſtie.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
